So I've done the work for you. This next clip that you're about to watch is actually a 12-minute video
that I have cut down to approximately like three to four minutes because I want y'all to get the
gist of this, but I'm hoping that it's enough to inspire you to go to YouTube and watch this video
in full. Barbara F. Walter doing a TED Talk on how civil wars start. I've been studying civil wars
for over 30 years. In 2017, I was asked to serve on a task force run by the CIA called the Political
Instability Task Force. It turns out that predicting civil war is possible. It turns out that only two
factors were highly predictive, and they weren't the ones the experts expected. The first was whether
a country was an inocracy. Inocracy is just a fancy term for partial democracy. It's a government
that's neither fully democratic nor fully autocratic. It's something in between. So think about Hungary
today. Hungary holds elections. Hungarians eagerly go out and vote. It's just that whoever wins those
elections can basically do whatever they want. The second factor was whether citizens in these
inocracies had formed political parties around identity rather than ideology. So rather than
joining a party because you were liberal or conservative, capitalist or communist, you joined a party
because you were black or white, Christian or Muslim, Serb or Croat. And I could see that both of these
factors were emerging in my own country, and they were emerging at a surprisingly fast rate.
The U.S.'s democracy has been downgraded three times since 2016. Between December of 2020 and early
2021, the United States was officially classified as an inocracy. Just a few weeks before the January 6th
insurrection, and it likely would have put the United States on the watch list. We also know who tends to
start civil wars. And again, it's not the people most of us think. It is not the poorest people in society. It is not the
people who are most oppressed by their government. The people who tend to start civil wars, especially ethnically
based civil wars, are the groups that had once been politically dominant but are in decline. In the United States, the
rise of militias has been driven primarily by white men who see America's identity changing in ways that directly
threatens their status. They were the ones who marched on the Capitol on January 6th. So why is this happening now? It's
happening now because of demographic change. The United States is in the midst of a major transition from a
country whose population is majority white to a country whose population will be majority non-white. I've
interviewed a lot of people who have lived through a civil war, and they all say the same thing. I didn't see it
coming. But there's no reason why we, the democracy-loving people of this world, can't create our own playbook
to prevent civil war. But to do that, we have to be brave enough to fight for real democracy, strong
democracy, because only by fighting for democracy can we ensure that we will truly get peace. Americans can
allow this transition to tear us apart. Or we could use it to come together to show the world how to
manage this change and in the process create a truly multi-ethnic, multi-religious democracy. So how do
you do this? To hear her ideas on what we should do, to get more information on civil wars, and to really
just get a better understanding of where we are and where we're going, I hope you all will take the time
to go watch this incredible TED talk on how civil wars start by Barbara F. Walter. Don't say I ain't
never told you nothing.